A Guide to the Papers of Alan Cheuse, 1976-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Alan Cheuse 1976-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10726
This collection consists of ca. 1,025 items (10 Hollinger boxes, 3.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Alan Cheuse of Fairfax, Virginia, placed his papers on loan to the Library on July 20, 1987. The papers were purchased by the Library on September 11, 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
Cheuse was born in Perth Amboy, New Jersey, the son of Philip and Henrietta (Diamond) Cheuse. He was educated at Lafayette College and Rutgers University, receiving his Ph.D. from Rutgers in 1974. His career has been one of variety; he has been a reporter for Fairchild Publications; a staff member of the Kirkus Review Service; a member of the editorial board for Studies on the Left; a teacher of history and English at the Butler Institute, Guadalajara, Jalisco, Mexico; a faculty member at Bennington College, Bennington, Vermont, 1970-1978; a co-director of the Bennington Summer Writing Workshops; and a visiting lecturer on creative writing at various institutions, including the University of Michigan and the University of Virginia.
Since leaving the teaching field in 1978, Cheuse has devoted himself to a full-time career as a writer, including reviews for many national magazines and National Public Radio, short stories, three works of fiction, Candace & Other Stories (1980), The Bohemians (1982), and the Grandmothers' Club (1986), and an autobiographical book entitled, Fall Out of Heaven (1987).
Scope and Content Information
The papers of novelist and book reviewer Alan Cheuse (1940- ), contain ca. 1,025 items (10 Hollinger boxes, 3.5 linear feet), 1976-1987. They include: drafts of Fall Out of Heaven (1987); his short stories, both in hard copy and on diskettes, and his book reviews, many of which were prepared for "All Things Considered" on National Public Radio; personal and professional correspondence; newsclippings; printed material; interviews; and photographs.
Much of this material was generated by Cheuse during his association with the University of Virginia in the spring of 1987 as a visiting lecturer in the Creative Writing Program of the English Department, especially his correspondence and the manuscripts for Fall Out of Heaven.
The collection is arranged in three series. The manuscript series is entirely composed of various drafts of Fall Out of Heaven, including typescripts, computer print-outs, drafts with editors' corrections and comments, a setting copy, page proof, and material related to the book.
Cheuse's book Fall Out of Heaven incorporates the previously unpublished autobiographical novel of his father, Philip K. Cheuse (1910-1983), who was born near Kiev, Russia, and served as a lieutenant in the Red Air Force, mainly flying against rebellious eastern tribesmen near Khiva, Uzbekistan, Soviet Union. After many adventures, Philip Cheuse eventually emigrated to the United States and led a more conventional life in Perth Amboy, New Jersey. The novel also relates the conflicts between Cheuse and his father and includes Cheuse's own journey to the Soviet Union and the Orient in 1986, where he traced his father's footsteps.
Related materials include: the original manuscript of Philip Cheuse's autobiography, notes kept by Alan Cheuse on his trip through the Soviet Union for the book, travel literature about the Soviet Union, a synopsis of the book, and a blue line copy of the book jacket.
The correspondence with friends, colleagues, and publishers is both personal and professional and generally discusses their projects and work, personal lives, and Cheuse's books and reviews. It also consists of arrangements for readings, lectures, and book signings; submissions for publication; grants; and job openings.
A few of the correspondents include: E.L. Doctorow (March 15, 1986); Stuart Wright (November 12, 1986); Richard Ford (December 18, 1986, & April 8 & 27, 1987); Annie Dillard (March 28, April 1 & 23, 1987); and Josephine Humphreys regarding the telling of stories (February 19, 1987). Topics include: "Southern writing" (December 18, 1986); Kim Basinger (February 7, 1987); a memorial service for Bernard Malamud (March 30, 1987); and India and Pakistan (April 11, 1987). The Fall Out of Heaven correspondence includes a letter from Cheuse, March 29, 1987, explaining the process of writing the book about his father and his own childhood. The correspondence with his publisher, Gibbs M. Smith, Inc., concerns the publication of The Grandmothers' Club and Fall Out of Heaven.
The series of miscellaneous papers includes: an article and research notes on Barbara Mandrell; book reviews by Alan Cheuse, arranged by the last name of the authors with reviews of groups of books at the end; a file on the Bennington College Writing Workshops, when Cheuse was Acting Director; an interview with Jack Nicholson, with his notes and revisions; miscellaneous short stories, articles, etc., including "Writing for the Ear, Reading for the Eye," "Heart," "Ossuary," "Tennessee Waltz," "Seals," "Cover," "Mexico" (possibly the same as "Not Quite at Home"), "A Couple of White Guys Sitting Around Writing," "Roads," "Bio," "Gold Threads Among the Silver," "Land of Cotton," "Encounter in Moscow," "Sources of Country Music," "Big Mouth," and Mean Tide; photographs of Alan Cheuse and others; printed announcements of readings, publication dates, and workshops; research material for an article entitled "Just Folks" concerning country music and Opryland photographs; reviews of Cheuse's The Grandmothers' Club; and a vita file.
Organization
The collection is arranged in three series: 1) Manuscripts of Fall Out of Heaven and Related Material (Boxes 1-6); 2) Correspondence (Boxes 7-8); 3) Miscellaneous Materials (Boxes 9-10)
Contents List
- Series I: Materials Concerning Fall Out of Heaven
  - Original Manuscript by Philip K. Cheuse (2 folders) [ante 1983] (Box 1)
  - Original Manuscript by Philip K. Cheuse - Copies (2 folders) [ante 1983] (Box 1)
  - Original Manuscript of Philip K. Cheuse - Second Copies (2 folders) [ante 1983] (Box 2)
  - Fall Out of Heaven Notes 1986 (Box 2)
  - Travel Literature for the Soviet Union 1986 (Box 2)
  - Synopsis for Fall Out of Heaven & Related Material ca. 1987 (Box 2)
  - Fall Out of Heaven - Second Drafts (6 folders) ca.1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Fall Out of Heaven - Various Drafts (3 folders) ca.1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Fall Out of Heaven - Computer Print-out (2 folders) ca.1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Fall Out of Heaven - Drafts with corrections by the editors (5 folders) 1987 (Box 5)
  - Fall Out of Heaven - Setting Copy (3 folders) 1987 (Box 6)
  - Fall Out of Heaven - Page Proof (2 folders) 1987 (Box 6)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence (6 folders) 1985 Mar-1987 Mar (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (4 folders) 1987 Apr-Aug (Box 8)
  - Correspondence ca. 1987 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence re Fall Out of Heaven 1982-1987 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Gibbs M. Smith, Inc. (2 folders) 1985-1987, n.d. (Box 8)
- Series III: Miscellaneous Material
  - Article re Barbara Mandrell n.d. (Box 9)
  - Articles not by Alan Cheuse 1981 & n.d. (Box 9)
  - Bennington Writing Workshops 1985-1987 (Box 9)
  - Book Reviews by Alan Cheuse: A-W (4 folders) [ca. 1984-1987] (Box 9)
  - Interview with Jack Nicholson 1983 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Short Stories, Articles, etc. 1976-1987 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Material 1982-1987 (Box 10)
  - Photographs ca. 1986-1987 (Box 10)
  - Printed Material 1985-1987 (Box 10)
  - Research Materials for "Just Folks," an Article re Country Music Stars 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Reviews of The Grandmothers' Club 1986-1987 (Box 10)
  - "The Seals" (Various Drafts) 1987 (Box 10)
  - Vita Information ca. 1978-1987 (Box 10)